A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Winthrop Rockefeller papers, Series AD FA403
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Winthrop Rockefeller papers, Series AD
1912-1976
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Winthrop
FA403
7.87 Cubic Feet
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four groups, primarily based on subject matter:
Family and Personal
Winrock Farms
Speeches, Publications, and Publicity Materials
Audiovisual Materials
Biographical / Historical
Winthrop Rockefeller, born May 1, 1912, was the fourth son of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. After attending the Lincoln School in New York City and the Loomis School in Connecticut, Winthrop enrolled at Yale University for a short period of time. After leaving Yale, Winthrop worked as a roughneck in the oilfields in Texas.
After serving in the Army during World War II, Winthrop eventually moved to Arkansas in 1953. Purchasing a 927-acre tract of land on Petit Jean Mountain, he built Winrock Farms, which would become famous for breeding Santa Gertrudis cattle.
In 1948, Winthrop Rockefeller married Barbara "Bobo" Sears, amidst a flurry of publicity. They had one son, Winthrop Paul Rockefeller, and divorced in 1954. In 1956, Winthrop remarried Jeanette Edris, who had two children from a previous marriage. The couple divorced in 1971.
In 1955, Winthrop accepted a position as Chairman of the Arkansas Industrial Development Commission, serving for eight years.
Although his bid for governor of Arkansas was unsuccessful in 1964, Winthrop ran again in 1966 and won, making him the first Republican governor in Arkansas in 94 years. He was re-elected in 1968, and served until January 1971 as governor.
Winthrop Rockefeller died of cancer on February 22, 1973 at the age of 60.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
File Plan
Former classification: III 2 AD -- Rockefeller Family Archives, Record Group 2 (Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller), Series AD (Winthrop Rockefeller)
Related Materials
For materials that complement or enhance an understanding of Winthrop Rockefeller's life and work, researchers may wish to consult the following collections at the Rockefeller Archive Center:
-Winthrop Rockefeller Collection
-William E. Davis Photographs (P/1068)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was collected by Rockefeller Family and Associates (Room 5600) and later transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center by Room 5600.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: corrrespondence, speeches, and publications.
Arkansas
- Winthrop Rockefeller Papers, 1912-1976; AD
  - Family and Personal, 1912-1976
    Arrangement
    Family and Personal is arranged roughly alphabetically, and includes materials related to Winthrop's personal life, including correspondence and clippings maintained by the Rockefeller Family Office.
    - Army Letters, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anne Bartley, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Folder restricted - contains closed materials.
    - Bruce Bartley, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - College, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to Winthrop Rockefeller, 1921-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Winthrop Rockefeller, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Winthrop Rockefeller, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Winthrop Rockefeller, 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, Retyped, 1923-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Winthrop and Bobo Rockefeller Divorce, 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, Winthrop Rockefeller to Abby and John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1933-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Estate of Winthrop Rockefeller, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Estate of Winthrop Rockefeller (Jewelry, Chinese Porcelain, Furniture Storage, Rugs, Antique Automobiles, Paintings and Drawings, Paintings, Prints), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Estate of Winthrop Rockefeller (Office Furniture - Tower Building - Little Rock, Arkansas, 467 Via Lola, Palm Springs, California, Cal-Ceram, Inc.), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence, 1966-1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Hawks Apartment, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Income Tax, 1937-1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Anne Bartley Papa Trust, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Perotti, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller Archives, 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Army Service, 1941-1948 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Army Service, Letters re: Injury, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Death, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Death, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Death, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Death, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 25A)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Death, Press Release and Memorial Service Program, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Financial Statements, 1912-1939 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Finances, 1930-1943 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Finances, 1591 Club, Inc., 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Finances, Allowance, 1920-1934 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Finances, Sign of the Fiddle Inn, Inc., 1951-1962 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Finances, Mr. R., Jr. Chase Bank and Morgan Loans, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, General, 1912-1968 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, General, 1912-1968 (Box 4, Folder 33A)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, General, 1939-1944 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, General, 1944-1961 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Gifts, 1912-1949 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1953-1960 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Separation and Divorce, 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Trips, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Mrs. Winthrop Rockefeller (Bobo), Publicity, 1948-1958 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Mrs. Winthrop Rockefeller (2nd) (Jeanette), 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Mrs. Winthrop Rockefeller (2nd) (Jeanette), Gifts, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Winthrop Paul Rockefeller, 1948-1971 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Separation Agreement and Property Settlement, Winthrop and Bobo Rockefeller, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Stork Restaurant, Inc. (Billingsley), 1964-1967 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Trusts, McLeod Trusts Checkbook, 1967-1973 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Winrock Farms, 1954-1973
    Winrock Farms is arranged alphabetically and contains items related to the Farm, mostly publicity material on the annual cattle production sales at Winrock Farms.
    - Jane Bartlett, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Cattle Sale Materials, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Fine Arts Inventory, Winrock Farms, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Memo re: Winrock Farms, August 21, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - "MURROCK New Community Project Pre-Application", 1972 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Souvenir Folder, 7th Annual Production Sale, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Souvenir Folder, 9th Annual Production Sale, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Souvenir Folder, 10th Annual Production Sale, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Souvenir Folder, 11th Annual Production Sale, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Souvenir Folder, 12th Annual Production Sale, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Souvenir Folder, 13th Annual Production Sale, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller Archives: Reports, 1969-1973 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Winrock, Archival Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Winrock Farms, General, 1954-1963 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Winrock Farms, Winthrop Rockefeller Archives, 1971-1976 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Speeches, Publications, and Publicity Materials, 1937-1973
    Speeches, Publications, and Publicity Materials is arranged alphabetically, and made up of several boxes of speeches made by Winthrop from 1937 through 1967, as well as publications by or about Winthrop Rockefeller. The majority of these materials were generated during Withrop's campaigns for Arkansas governor or during his governorships.
    - 1964 Governor Campaign (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - 1966 Campaign for Governor (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - 1968 and 1970 Campaign Contributions (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - "A Farewell Address" by Governor Winthrop Rockefeller, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - "An Era of Excellence: 1953-1973" Program (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Campaign for Governor, 1964 (Contributions) (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Draft of Doubleday Book by Winthrop Rockefeller, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - "Executive Clemency and the Death Penalty," "The Catholic University Law Review", 1972 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - "Here I Stand...on Civil Rights / Education / Labor / Welfare" (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - "Inaugural Address", 1969 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Inauguration Day Program, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Instruction Notebook for "The Rockefeller Years" (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - "Our Freedom Is Not Free", 1972 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - "Pre-Inaugural Service of Dedication", 1967 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Requests for Information, 1964-1972 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller Appreciation Dinner, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Campaign Photographs (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Gubernatorial, General, 1964-1972 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller, Portrait Photographs (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Speech Correspondence, 1952-1967 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Speeches, 1937-1949 (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Speeches, 1950-1954 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Speeches, 1955-1959 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Speeches, 1960-1964 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Speeches, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Speeches, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 89)
    - Speeches, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - "This I Believe" (Box 11, Folder 91)
    - "Win Rockefeller Family Album" (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - "The Win Rockefeller Story" (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - Oversized Campaign Materials (Box 12, Folder 94)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller Audiovisual materials, 1957-1973
    Chronological by year of creation
    When requesting to view films please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1902).
    All inquires to view films require advanced notice of at least 24 hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those not available in modern formats, may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
    Sound recordings; Moving Images
    - Winrock: An Interim Report, 1957; Sound, Color, 36 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1731)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
      Scope and Contents note
      Arkansas: building and development of Winrock Farms; Santa Gertrudis cattle breeding program; obtaining water supply for farm; Winthrop Rockefeller's daily schedule; building local school and clinic; Petitjean Airport; Winthrop Rockefeller's personal reflections on the Arkansas Industrial Development Commission; film written and narrated by Walter McGraw
    - Winrock Farm: A Progress Report, 1957; Sound, Color, 20 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1730)
      Overview of Arkansas cattle breeding programs and construction of Winrock Farm, written and narrated by Walter McGraw.
    - Housing in the Middle East, 1960; Sound, Black and white, 6 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1391)
      Access copy available.
      Tour of model homes with Winthrop Rockefeller. Narration in a Middle Eastern language.
    - Self-Portrait: Winthrop Rockefeller, 1963; Color, Black and white, 30 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1728)
      Interview by Harry Reasoner for CBS about Winthrop Rockefeller's work at Winrock Farm and his life in Arkansas (includes original commercials).
    - A Time for Man, 1966; Sound, Black and white, 30 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1672)
      Film produced for Winthrop Rockefeller gubernatorial campaign in Arkansas.
    - On the People's Business, 1968; Sound, Black and white, 30 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1727)
    - To Do Justly, 1968; Sound, Color, 60 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1737)
      Winthrop Rockefeller campaign film with Bob Hope, Jeannette Rockefeller, and John D. Rockefeller IV.
    - The Infantryman: Our Country, 1972 November 11; Sound, Color, 20 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1729)
      Groundbreaking ceremony for National Infantry Museum at Ft. Benning, Georgia (Winthrop RockefellerWR was chairman of national fundraising campaign for museum), introduction to history of US infantry.
    - Winthrop Rockefeller Memorial Service, 1973 March 4; Sound, Color, 66 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1736)
      Footage of ceremony at Winrock Farms, Arkansa: Monsignor O'Connor gives eulogy, Dr. Daniel Grant speaks about John D. Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller speaks about Winthrop Rockefeller.R
    - Winthrop Rockefeller Memorial Service - Part 1, 1973 March 4; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 32 minutes (Box 1, Reel AV 9908)
    - Winthrop Rockefeller Memorial Service - Part 2, 1973 March 4; 1/4 inch audio tape; Sound, 33 minutes (Box 1, Reel AV 9909)